Hey everyone, and thanks for dropping
back into the cryptoverse.
Today we're going to talk about Bitcoin
and how it has at least temporarily
stalled out at the 50week moving
average. If you guys like the content,
make sure you subscribe to the channel,
give the video a thumbs up, and also
check out the sale on ITC Premium at
into the cryptoverse.com.
As a reminder, you only have one more
day to get a ticket to the ITC
conference before the ticket prices go
up. So, they're going to go up on
September 1st. So, if you are already
planning on coming, make sure you guys
go ahead and get your ticket. The main
conference day will be November 21st,
but we'll have some stuff uh the night
before as well. And there'll also be a
party the night of the conference. So,
make sure you guys check that out. Links
in the description below. Uh or you can
just go to bjaminc.com
and then go over to the conference tab.
It'll take place in Miami. All right,
let's go ahead and jump in. So, Bitcoin
rallied back up to the 50we moving
average. And and this is kind of the
area where I've said before is oftent
times the line in the sand for Bitcoin
in terms of where the bears would put
their final stand if the bare market is
to go on. And what I mean by that is
when you look through the context of
history, every time that Bitcoin has
dropped below the 50we moving average,
like in 2014, 2018, uh late 2021, and of
course late 2025, every time that that's
happened, that marked the end of the
bull market.
And then when Bitcoin has gotten above
the 50we moving average
in 2015, in 2019, and in 2023, that has
always marked the beginning of the bull
market and the nail in the coffin to the
bare market. Now, the difficult thing is
the assessment that some people for sure
know what's going to happen here. And
you know, a lot of people are are
looking at at the what happened over
here in 2023. And and listen, I'm not
unsympathetic to the view. I mean, if
Bitcoin gets above the 50 moving
average, happy to drop the bear goggles.
Happy to drop it and and let's get the
bull market started. But
there's this
reality as well, right? If you look at
2023, you can certainly say, look, we we
rallied through the 200 day moving
average like 2023.
Therefore, is it not the same thing?
Maybe it is. But there are times
throughout history in in Bitcoin's bare
markets where we rallied above the 200
day moving average. And I actually
pointed this out earlier this year. I I
was on a Twitter space with people and
they were like, "Oh, well, if we get
above the 200 day moving average,
Bitcoin has never been in a bare market
above it." I'm like, "Well, that
conveniently ignores 2014, which kind is
kind of weak because we only barely got
above it. But in 2015, we had a massive
breakout above the 200 day moving
average and then we still came back
down. But what you'll notice in 2015 is
when Bitcoin blasted through the 200 day
moving average where it got rejected at
was the 50WE, right? And so that is why
I say that this is the line in the sand
because there there also are times in
Bitcoin's bare markets like in 2018 and
in 2022 where we rally up to the 50we
moving average and get rejected. So, you
know, I know that 2015 maybe isn't the
best comparison. That's a preh having
year. Doesn't really feel like 2015 is
the best comparison, but I think the
2018 comparison has some legs to it. And
and the the reason I say that is is just
simply because of the you know this how
how similar these moves have played out
like the low in February
in both cases the slightly lower low in
the summer. And again what's interesting
about the lower low is that Bitcoin's
lower low in the summer of 2018 was at
5700 and then the lower low in the
summer of 2026 was at 57,000. And and so
then what happened in both of those
cases after Bitcoin swept the February
low, we got one more counter trend
rally. Now earlier this year when we put
in the summer low, I said, "Look, we're
likely going to have a back in what?
Early this year, I said we'll likely
have a low in February. We'll likely
have a low in the summer." And you can
still get counter trend rallies on
either side of those. like you know the
the summer low can lead to a counter
trend rally but it doesn't necessarily
have to end the bare market. Now a lot
of people get upset with this but I'm
just showing you guys what has happened
before and
this is getting a little bit into the
weeds admittedly but fasten your seat
belt because we're going to look at the
4hour chart. I know you probably wonder
what fresh hell is this? But there's
something that that's kind of
interesting that caught my eye and I
don't know why, you know, this stood out
to me. But what's interesting in 2018
when Bitcoin had that rally to the
50week moving average if you look at you
you see where the breakout started like
the the the big move up the 4hour candle
where Bitcoin just started bolting
higher from that breakout from the
breakout it took uh 51 4hour candles to
reach the 50week moving average and then
that's where Bitcoin got rejected right
so 51 4hour candles from
from the breakout, right? So, from when
Bitcoin started the move because you can
see it was just kind of consolidating
and then a big move up 51 4hour candles.
So, I was looking at that and I was
like, "All right, well, I wonder what it
was this time around, you know, and
again, like I I this is this is one of
those things where yeah, maybe you're
maybe I'm looking for something, right?"
Okay, like you know, so maybe it's not
like the fairest comparison, but you see
the breakout candle right here. You I
mean, it's pretty clear, right? I mean,
you can see like it was consolidation
just like 2018 and you move up and then
you get the breakout candle from the
breakout candle to the 50week moving
average where we put in the local high
was also exactly 51 4hour candles. So I
I think like the difficult thing for me
is that there's a lot of people out
there saying that like this has never
happened before. Like we've never had a
rally like this in in a bare market. But
there is some validity to the idea that
Bitcoin rallied to the 50we moving
average in 2018
just like it did in 2026. The main
difference is when the rally occurred.
So in 2018 the rally topped in late
July. This time it was it you know we
find ourselves at the at the 50we moving
average in late August but we have had
rallies into August 2022. Bitcoin had a
nice rally off the summer low into
August. In fact, if you were to look at
a price range from the from the summer
low in 2018 to where it topped at, it
was a little over a 40% move in 2022.
From the summer low to that local top,
it was a little over a 40% move. And
then from the 2026 low to that move that
we just got was just over 40%. So, like
I I would have to push back a little bit
on the idea that this hasn't happened
before because it clearly has, right?
Like Bitcoin has clearly found summer
lows, rallied 40%, and then still gone
on to go a little bit lower later on in
Q4. Now, that does not mean you can't go
buy Bitcoin. Like I've been saying since
July 1st I it's a hard game to figure
out where the low is going to be. But if
if you know everyone on Twitter is going
to come after me and and say well you
know if you're still speculating about a
future low you're completely left in the
dust. Guys like I'm not saying you can't
buy. Like there's no I and by the way if
you think the low is in refusing to buy
after just a a small move up after a
market cycle low, right? Right? I mean,
like it would have been like saying
you're not going to buy Bitcoin in early
2019 because it was at 5,000 and not
3,000 or like you're not going to buy it
in 2023 because it was at, you know, uh,
off the low. It was at like 23,000
instead of 15,000. In the time, at the
time it felt hard to buy, but you look
back a few years later and it's like,
you know what, still buying in those
areas at the 50we moving average was
better than not buying. Okay. So once
you had a weekly move above the 50week
moving average, you can see that that is
what kind of put the nail in the coffin
of the bare market. Now some people have
said, well, we got rejected by the 50we.
And there is some validity to the idea
that we've at least stalled out at it.
But stalling out at the 50week moving
average in itself is not evidence that
we are going to be rejected by it. even
on attempts where Bitcoin gets through
the 50week moving average, it still will
often stall out at it for a few weeks.
Okay? So, don't use Bitcoin stalling out
at the 50week moving average as
necessarily evidence that it can't break
through.
But listen, I'm just here to say if if
you're going to if you're going to look
at these moves that we've had in 2026
and say that it's never happened before,
that's not true, right? like every
summer from every summer low that we've
had right for the last couple of cycles,
Bitcoin has rallied 40% off the summer
low and then still went lower a little
bit later on. You know, one of the
things that I've talked about before as
well is the idea of an October low. And
it doesn't have to be October, right? I
mean, if if the low is not in, it could
occur in September, could be November,
December, January, who knows, right?
When it'll be. But there's also, you
know, one thing to I just want to like
kind of put it out there is that in the
last three market cycles, the actual
drop to the market cycle bottom did not
occur until after the midterm election.
So again, the midterms are in early
November. And what you'll notice is that
Bitcoin has always dropped to its market
cycle low after the midterm election.
So, I don't know if that's what's going
to happen again. Like, maybe everyone's
going to sit around through October and
be like, "All right, the coast is clear
and then, you know, and and then it
happens."
I would still be slightly in favor if
the low is not in of of maybe October
and then the people that are waiting for
November, December, you know, maybe they
shouldn't wait. But I just want to show
you guys how there's all these
similarities through the cycles, right?
the the counter trend rally like off a
summer low that then stalls out and then
goes lower a little bit later. Again,
guys, if we get weekly closes, you know,
above the 50we like we did in 2019 and
2023 and 2015, I'm happy to drop the
bias. But it's also sort of worth
acknowledging that every break above the
50we moving average after the bare
market never occurred in the midterm
year, right? It always occurred in the
pre-h having year. Now, it did occur
earlier in the pre-h having year. Uh the
one back over here in 2015 was in
October and then this one was in April
and then this one was in March, right?
but is going from March of the preh
havinging year to August of the midterm
year. Like that seems like a a kind of a
big jump. I'm not saying it's
impossible, but again, there's like
there's a reason to have some
skepticism, I would say. Right. There
skepticism. Again, in my opinion,
historically, the correct strategy,
which is the strategy I've employed in
both 2018 and 2022, was to start buying
after the summer low, and whatever comes
your way, you deal with it. You don't
take out your emotions on anyone else.
You deal with it. I started buying in
the summer of 2018, and I got wrecked at
the end of the year. I started buying in
the summer of 2022 and I got wrecked.
And I thought I thought we were going to
go lower back then. In fact, my biggest
regret was not buying more.
So,
we can't know until the end of the year.
Again, it's more of an academic
exercise, but it just goes to show you
that saying that this type of stuff
hasn't happened before is objectively
not true, right? Like, it it has
happened before. That doesn't mean that
the way that I'm viewing the market is
necessarily the correct one. But to
dismiss it as not having happened is in
de in direct contradiction to what has
happened after the summer low in the
last two bare markets. 40% rallies that
then stalled out in July and August
and then we led into the market cycle
bottom. So we'll see if it plays out one
week at a time. If you guys like the
content, subscribe, give the video a
thumbs up, and again, if you do want to
come to the ITC conference, uh, make
sure you get your ticket. September 1st
is when prices are going to go up, so
you have at least one more day to get
those tickets before prices increase.
Hope to see you guys there. Thank you
guys for tuning in. Subscribe and I'll
see you next time. Bye.